Downloaded from
YTS.MX
Official YIFY movies site:
This is the 52nd annual celebration
of the October Revolution
taking place in November
in Moscow's Red Square.
AFTER WORLD WAR II POLAND WAS SURRENDERED
TO THE COMMUNIST SOVIET EMPIRE
Moscow Military District troops,
including the Armored Missile Divisions
parade in front of party leaders
and members of government.
IN 1980, FOLLOWING SEVERAL ATTEMPTS
AT RESISTANCE, POLES CREATED "SOLIDARITY",
A 10-MILLIONS-STRONG OPPOSITION MOVEMENT
HEADED BY LECH WAŁĘSA
WALESA
MAN OF HOPE
WRITTEN BY
- We have company again.
- That's possible.
Can they stop us?
The most famous journalist
from the West?
They're here for our safety.
It seems to me that this interview
could be very inconvenient for them.
Boys, clear up your toys.
Go wash your hands.
Sławek, take this away.
I'll check your hands, all right?
- A white shirt.
- No. I didn't want this interview.
Bogdan, take this.
Wear a tie at least.
No! I'm not going to suffocate
for that brazen hag.
This is the home of the man
who leads a 10-million-member union?
He was recently given this place
by the authorities.
He accepted an apartment
from the authorities he's opposing?
Six kids and no money to live on.
'Solidarity' didn't protest.
Are you sure?
What is he like?
He's full of contradictions.
And surprises.
I'm Oriana Fallaci.
It is a cold afternoon in Gdańsk,
blanketed with snow and anxiety.
Wait, wait, wait.
Before we begin, we need to
agree on a few things.
I'm a simple worker,
but I don't feel inferior...
Not inferior to generals,
to prime ministers or to you.
So let me ask the first question:
Will this interview help me or hurt me?
Listen, Mr. Wałęsa.
I can't tell you if you will
benefit from this or not.
It really depends on what you say.
And I'm the one asking questions.
Let's begin.
7 months ago, hardly anybody
knew your name abroad or in Poland.
Today you're one of the most famous
people in the world.
When you're in Italy, you're welcomed
like a head of state. A movie star...
Stop, stop, stop, stop.
Why?
You have an authoritarian,
dictatorial style.
I do, too. So now we have a problem.
Let's try this: I'll be nice to you
and you'll be nice to me.
Otherwise, we'll tear
each other to pieces.
We've talked once before. Why again?
Because I need to make sure
I've understood you correctly.
Brezhnev was clear on one thing: in Poland,
enemies of socialism are carrying out
counterrevolutionary activities.
And the Soviet Union will never
abandon its communist Polish allies.
This is only barking
meant to scare people off.
Aren't you afraid of responsibility
towards your country and history?
- No, no, no...
- Or that you're not the right person?
I am a man of faith and I know
that the times call for someone like me.
DECEMBER 1970
12 December 1970
the Council of Ministers has approved
an increase in prices of consumer goods.
The prices of meat preserves
are rising by 17.6%.
Wheat and rye flour by 16%.
Milk - 8%.
Jam and marmalade - 36.8%.
Roasted grain coffee - 92.1%.
Cream of wheat - 23%.
I made it, I'm here!
Go now, Mr. Wałęsa!
Thank God you've taken a day off.
Go, go!
I'll wipe Danuta's feet myself.
Put on something warm.
It's freezing.
Lech!
Where's your scarf?
- I'll do it.
- No, you shouldn't bend over.
Your hair must be done. Don't want you
looking like this in the delivery room.
Eyebrows, too. Do you like them thick
or do you prefer a 'surprised' look?
And I'll throw in a perm for free.
Right. How on earth
am I going to pay for Christmas? Eh?
Meat and sugar prices are up by 30%.
If I had a cripple or a baby at home,
I could skip the line at the shop...
And those bastards boast about
the falling cost of train engines. And?
- It works great. Like a Mercedes.
- What else did you expect?
- Only three of these in the whole city.
- I don't know how to repay you.
Let's leave through the back door.
You know how envious people get.
Krysia! Hurry up.
We're closing shop.
- It's a war out there!
- What?
The shipyard workers are out on the streets!
GDAŃSK
14 DECEMBER, 1970
It's gorgeous!
The city is in real turmoil.
What?
Beautiful.
How are you, Danuta?
I'll be right back.
- There's bloodshed in the streets.
- What are you saying?
Sell these if I don't come back.
Lech!
People, control yourselves!
Calm down!
Go away!
Don't let them provoke you!
Rysiek!
- How did it go?
- I have at least 30 signatures.
Last name?
Wałęsa.
- First name?
- Lech.
- Father's name?
- Bolesław.
Date of birth?
September 29, 1943.
- Place?
- Popowo, Bydgoszcz district.
- Occupation?
- Electrician.
What kind?
Wałęsa the Electrician.
- You want me to punch him?
- Wait.
Let the bastard show off.
Place of employment?
Gdansk Shipyards, Department W4,
I deal with installations.
- Address?
- Gdansk, Beethoven Str. 30d.
Education?
- Basic vocational school in Lipno.
- Marital status?
Married. That's the thing...
My wife's about to give birth
to our first child. She's all alone.
Hands on the table.
- Were you on the Strike Committee?
- I was.
- You were pushing for revolt.
- I'm all for compromise.
- You started a counter-revolution.
- It's the government that started it.
- You were seen demolishing shops.
- You set fire to the Committee Building.
But my wife... I don't even know
if it's a boy or a girl.
You'll find out... 5 years from now.
Hands on the table!
- I did not demolish anything.
- You were instigating a riot.
I was trying to stop them.
- We have 7 witnesses.
- I have a witness, too.
- Who? A Jehovah's witness?
- The local militia commander.
You wanted to overthrow the government.
- I was trying to calm people down.
- We'll see. Nawiślak, call Walczewski.
Does "Wałęsa" ring a bell?
Walczewski says there was a guy
with a mustache trying to stop the riot.
Well, well. You're in luck.
Sign this, lucky guy.
And get out!
- What is this? A witness statement?
- None of your business. Sign it.
- And this.
- What's this?
Says here you will obey the law.
- Why should I sign this?
- Don't you want to obey the law?
- I do.
- Then sign it.
And this.
Sit!
What's this?
- You want me to be a snitch?
- Can't you read?
You will visit us as a consultant
from time to time.
To prevent further misfortune.
Do you want us to let you go?
We're all decent people here.
Don't worry about your family.
We'll take care of your son...
Son?
- ...and of your wife.
- I have a son...?
For now you do.
Are you signing it or not?
There are others waiting.
You're free to go, Wałęsa.
Danuta...
You're here...
My son.
I have a son.
They let you out.
Are you hurt?
Just an interrogation.
And then I signed something.
Lech, what did you sign?
They said they'd hurt you or the baby
so I would have signed anything
apart from the betrayal
of God or my country.
How did you get in here?
- Please get out.
- This is my son.
No visitors are allowed.
- I have the right to see my son.
- You're not allowed in here.
When did you realize you're a leader?
My friends ask: Why do you interfere?
But I like interfering.
In December 1970 and August 1980,
I interfered...
Because nobody else wanted to.
When I worked for the opposition,
I was the only one willing
to go to meetings.
I was the only one
who wanted to speak.
Today it's the same, because I know
how far we can go with our demands.
I know the reality of this country.
Polish Film Chronicle, 1971
A special Central Party Committee
has made an emergency assessment
of the dramatic events in Gdańsk.
The new head of the Committee, Edward
Gierek, has arrived at the Shipyard.
I urgently appeal to all shipyard workers
GDAŃSK SHIPYARD
JANUARY 1971
and to all working people of Poland.
Our aim is to reach consensus.
Therefore, we need your support.
So, you will help us, won't you?
Hey! Mijak! Mijak!
No mask? Are you crazy?
Come on. Let's go. Careful.
Director?
As a labor inspector, I've made
several requests for equipment.
Haven't I? For safety masks?
Sand-blasting without a mask
is not allowed.
Is that funny to you?
Why talk to me?
You've got the union.
The union takes care of its own holidays,
not our safety masks.
Listen, friend, the director is too busy to
deal with an employee's personal business.
It's not personal business,
it's the workers' business.
Then get back to work, workers!
Unless you don't like your jobs here.
Why aren't you working?
What's going on?
- A power cut.
- Again?
- Power cut? How can we do our work?
- You'll work through the night.
Those guys will learn how to play
before we get the power back.
Do something, Lech.
You are a social labor inspector.
What do you want me to do about it?
Man, as a labor resource,
can achieve incredible goals.
Working under our leaders' guidance is a
source of pride, joy, and inspiration.
However, under capitalism,
it's a whole different matter.
There, the working class
must constantly defend its rights.
Therefore I move that
we declare our support
for striking dockers in Brazil
and farmers in Thailand.
Who's in favor?
Raise your hands higher.
Who's against?
I can't see anyone.
And one more issue to be presented
on behalf of the staff by Czesław Mijak.
As imperialism tiptoes around us,
on its wolf's feet,
it is our duty to kill it off.
Since each year brings
further progress in our work,
I motion for the introduction
of voluntary penalties for those
who failed to meet last year's goals.
You want us to steal from ourselves?
Leave it.
Potatoes are more expensive
than our ships.
Are power failures our fault?
And shortages of sheet metal?
First Secretary Gierek broke
his promises, cheated the nation.
He does as he pleases, without the
consent of the working class.
Silence! What is this?
Stop all this! The issue is settled!
You've had your consultations.
That was a chance to have your say.
We're having a vote
on Comrade Mijak's proposal.
Let's vote democratically.
Openly. Who's in favor?
Who's against?
I see we have a controversy.
I'll break the bastard in two.
Goddamn snitch!
Where does Mijak live?
Good. You're here...
They stole the door to the john
And there's a draft now.
- Father's sick. Electricity's weak.
- Shhh... Shut it, woman!
They're not here to help
but to get revenge.
Close the door, then.
Invite your guests in.
No, no, we'll be going.
Maybe some other time.
Let's drop it...
Go on, beat me up.
They gave me wood for the stove
and promised
to hook up electricity.
Mijak.
I'll hook it up for you.
What are you doing?
Lech, let's go. You promised
to help me with the laundry.
- Catch some sun. I'll help tomorrow.
- You're working tomorrow.
The thing is, I'm not.
- How come?
- Just like that.
Jesus! They fired you?
What did you do this time?
I said one thing too many.
Tell me exactly what you said.
That Gierek has betrayed
the working class.
Jesus Christ!
That they're traitors, they didn't build
a monument for people they killed in 1970.
How are we going to pay for things?
We'll manage.
Now, where are the stones?
Who taught you to act this way?
I am a man full of great internal anger.
I've had this anger in my heart
since I was a little boy.
And when you build up this much anger,
you start to be able to use it cleverly.
This is why I can control crowds
and I can control strikes.
One has to be full of anger in order
to control the holy anger of people.
One has to be able
to live with anger.
"THE WORKER", 1978
- Lech, please stay away from this.
- What if I can't?
They fired you from the shipyard.
You want to lose this new job, too?
And the bread?
- What do they want?
- Who?
KOR. The Workers' Defense Committee.
Society's only defense against
injustice is solidarity.
And mutual help.
That's why we, Polish intellectuals,
have established KOR,
the Workers' Defense Committee.
Its aim is to defend
and help the workers.
Signed by Jerzy Andrzejewski.
And they've put their addresses too.
Oh, there's more. We demand
an amnesty for all arrested workers.
As well as restoring them to their jobs.
This is good thinking.
HUNGER STRIKE
Good evening.
I'd like to say that your diagnosis is right
but your methods are shitty.
You're either a horseman or a horse.
You can't be both.
The Commies are sucking our blood,
and you're starving to spite them?
Where's the logic? This is not
the way to corner the beast.
Even if cornered, it can use its claws
and meanwhile you die of hunger.
You write about breaking the law,
labor ethics, workers' dignity...
Start from the grassroots. The ground,
the shoes, the socks, the black sausage...
Also, you're too smart for me.
And even I myself am too smart
for the regular worker.
I want to support your cause,
because it's a just cause.
Any cause I choose to support will win.
To sum up, your intentions are fine.
The rest is garbage.
I have to go.
Wait, wait. Who are you?
- What's your name?
- Lech Wałęsa. I thought I'd talk to you.
I need to go. My youngest is sick.
Here's my address if you need me.
Good bye.
What a guy - a working class chauvinist.
He's got balls, though.
But what if he's one of them?
- Why would he be?
- He's the only one who came in sober.
Let's see if he comes back.
Lech, have a look.
We're writing about you.
Citizen! Stop!
Your ID, please.
Let me smell your breath.
- Don't touch this.
- Why?
That's illegal.
Next time, don't use alcohol for printing.
You can smell it a mile off.
Leave it! Leave the baby!
Leave the pram!
What's this?
- What's going on here?
- What do you mean?
The kid's pissing on the floor.
- Her diaper needs changing.
- Then do it!
- I don't have one.
- Bring us a diaper.
A diaper. Now!
- Will a towel do?
- A bloody one? From an interrogation?
Bring a new one.
Not from the toilets!
Lock him up when he's done.
With the pram.
What's going on here?
- Why is the kid crying?
- She's hungry.
Jesus! What are you doing?
Don't worry, I'm healthy.
I've just given birth myself...
Mine's a girl, too. Come on...
Why are you wearing this filthy thing?
The uniform?
Should I go around naked?
My husband left me with three kids.
This child should be at home.
You're putting her at risk.
Let her see what kind
of country she lives in.
When is it going to end?
Soon. It will end soon.
Those guys are far more scared
than you.
- You think they won't open fire?
- I sincerely doubt it.
Good morning, Mrs. Danuta.
Where is my husband?
What are you doing here?
We've missed you.
Have you seen my ball, mister?
I've lost it.
You brutes don't even show
respect for a woman.
Why don't you get your gun
and shoot us?
- Easy, lady.
- Do you have a warrant?
I won't calm down
because you say so.
Here you are.
It's a regular search.
What are you rummaging in there for?
Do you have no shame?
If you're hungry, I will make you
something to eat.
Such attractive men and such pigs.
What are you doing there?
The broadcast!
Long live the Pope!
On the eve of Pentecost,
I join you in calling out:
Lord, let your Spirit descend.
Let your Spirit descend
and revive the face of the Earth,
the face of this land, of this country.
Is that your pram downstairs, Danuta?
Jesus Almighty!
It's my Magda!
Lech. You have visitors.
- Good morning.
- Will I be needed?
No. Not at all.
- Sit down, Mr. Wałęsa.
- No thanks, I'll stand.
- I just want to say, before you ask...
- We are not asking.
We're only worried about you.
You're so pale,
your hands are shaking.
Nothing is shaking.
May I go now?
Sit down.
Have a smoke.
I'll smoke,
but I'm telling you nothing.
- Are you a Pole?
- What else would I be?
Then why do you keep pushing
Poland into a precipice?
Me? I told you I wouldn't talk.
But you used to talk.
Right. True.
In the past I talked,
because I didn't have a choice.
We had a good rapport.
As representatives of law and order
we appreciate your cooperation.
And I regret it.
- I've told the opposition about this.
- Don't be such a smart-ass!
You signed the paper! You have 5 kids?
Your wife doesn't work, does she?
You will crawl begging for bread.
Do you want to be fired from here
like you were fired from the shipyard?
No need to shout!
I will never forsake my membership
in the Free Trade Union! Never!
And I will not be
disturbed at work.
I'm going back to my work.
I'm not afraid of the consequences.
You know, I've been arrested
lots of times.
Usually for 48 hours.
The prison's a good place for thinking.
You're locked up.
There's no noise.
I invented a system
for letting people know I was arrested.
Being in jail is pointless
if people don't know about it.
And how does your wife cope
with all this?
My wife is not bad at all.
I should say she's an ideal wife.
If it wasn't for her,
I'd be either divorced or dead.
Stabbed with a kitchen knife.
So I have no reason
to cheat on her.
And our 6 kids prove that
we make love often and we make it well.
Sometimes there are temptations.
I've told you already, I'm no saint.
Let's hope the Pope doesn't read this.
He's intelligent.
He understands people.
Militia calls it the fitness trail.
They will beat you here,
on the knee and the thigh.
When you fall,
they'll hit your kidneys.
You must control your fear.
Once you're walking,
keep your head protected.
But remember,
they don't want to cripple you.
They want to break your resolve.
To make you an offer you can't refuse.
When they see you've had enough,
they give you a piece of paper,
And say: "Sign it, you'll be released".
No big deal. A promise to follow
the law. Just sign it. Then you're off.
And this you should be afraid of.
Because one day someone will use
this piece of paper against you.
I've got it! I bought it.
Good.
- Let's play, Dad.
- Not now. Go to the kitchen.
Go on. Put the bread on the table.
What's up?
What?
They fired me.
Danuta...
Don't cry.
We're going to make it.
Don't worry. I'll find something.
People's cars break down.
I'll fix cars.
It will be OK.
I can't take this...
It's all right. Don't worry.
Recent actions undertaken
by the authorities
have nothing to do with patriotism.
They're ruthless towards real patriots,
they break fundamental laws.
My name is Lech Wałęsa.
I was fired from the Gdansk Shipyard
after 10 years of impeccable work.
Next year marks the 10th anniversary
of the bloody riots in December 1970.
We must build a monument.
If there is no monument until then,
I ask everyone coming to the
memorial service to bring a stone.
If everyone brings one, we can
build a monument out of those stones.
It will be a unique monument,
because the situation was unprecedented.
The Communist authorities
opened fire on their own people.
We want the law to overcome lawlessness.
We don't ever want Poles
to have to fight one another.
- He can speak.
- People love to listen to him.
If I'm not here next year -
my name's Lech Wałęsa - come get me.
But if I am here and some of you
are not, I will come and find you.
And? Was that worth it?
Already?
- There's no sugar, no milk for kids...
- No needles. Bloody needles.
Or thread. There's nothing at all.
35 years after the war
and you can't buy needles? Jesus.
We're going to starve to death.
And the people at the top see nothing...
Rich Man, Poor Man.
"Rich Man, Poor Man" is on!
Jesus, who can this be?
At this hour it can only be
the Security Service.
I'll go and see.
This won't take a minute.
- We're watching a show.
- We won't disturb.
- What is it?
- We need to talk.
They're listening. Come on up.
- It's in three days.
- What's in three days?
- There's lies, poverty and lawlessness.
- I know that. But what's in 3 days?
You know they fired
Anna Walentynowicz?
Everyone knows that.
It was revenge for her criticism.
Just before her retirement,
an old woman...
To humiliate her, let her die of hunger.
So it's in three days.
What?
A strike in the shipyard.
- People won't be ready.
- If we don't act now, they will lock us up.
You're the leader.
Lech, who else could do this?
For one, you are 100% Polish.
A Catholic, with a wife and 5 kids.
Six kids. Jesus, in three days?
You were on the strike committee
in December 1970.
People respect you.
It's today.
- Didn't I tell you?
- You didn't.
- He's not here.
- I can see he's not.
- Maybe they've caught him.
- Or he's out drunk somewhere.
Lech? We've paid him a visit,
we talked about this. So?
Do we wait or what?
- People won't follow us.
- Or maybe they will.
We're young. We have no families.
We're kids who risk nothing.
But they know and respect Lech.
So let's give him more time.
How much longer? I'm starving.
Let's start without him!
People, move it, it's a strike!
We're on strike! All shipyards!
- All of them?
- Say it's all of them!
The ship repair yard is on hold!
Let's go!
It's a strike!
Comrades! Have mercy on your country!
No one had mercy on us.
People!
Comrades!
So it has started!
They started without me.
I was supposed to be there.
I'm not visiting you in prison,
or at the cemetery.
They won't shoot this time.
I know this, so I'm telling you,
I wouldn't say it if I wasn't sure.
You want to take on the military,
the militia and Gierek?
They're making me take them on.
I know the best case scenario
is that they hurt me real bad.
I don't want to do this.
But I've got to.
I managed to get some meat.
Pork shoulder and sausage.
And remember this:
Whatever you do, come back alive.
Sell it if I don't come back.
Lech!
The wheel's come off.
He's on the way to the shipyard?
I'd say 'yes', but remember what happened
in 1970 after we got their leaders?
No! But if he reaches the shipyard,
I'll hold you personally responsible.
I forbid it!
You decide for yourselves.
Why ask me, anyway?
Suddenly no one wants to decide.
Neither Warsaw nor District
want anything to do with this.
I heard they even called Gierek
on holiday but they didn't reach him.
Stop!
Enough lawlessness and thuggery!
People, calm down!
Please calm down!
We're on strike.
Do you recognize me?
I worked at the shipyard
for 10 years. I was fired.
But deep down I am a shipyard worker
because people still trust me.
We will defend Anna Walentynowicz.
We're starting a sit-down strike.
Poland can't afford work stoppages.
All right. Bring in your representatives.
The rest of you, please go back to work.
Here are our demands.
A 2000 zloty raise for everyone.
A monument for those killed
in December 1970.
Anna Walentynowicz
must get her job back.
Have a seat.
Under the circumstances
I approve the request to reinstate
Anna Walentynowicz.
Send a car for Walentynowicz.
This salary raise...
...2000 zloty?
There's 16 thousand people working here.
You must know things are very serious.
All shipyards are on strike.
I'm not authorized to... all right.
This is how I see it.
I can't offer any more.
And I see there's nothing to look at.
Yes. 2000.
Yes, I realize it's a lot.
I guarantee it will solve the problem.
What's going on?
This tram stops here.
We're joining the strike.
A plaque instead of the monument.
Inform the headquarters.
Call Wałęsa.
All our demands have been met.
Let me through!
The strike is over!
You abandoned us!
We supported you.
All buses and trams in the city
are at a standstill.
And now you say it's over?! They're
going to crush us all like vermin!
You've betrayed us!
The whole city is on strike!
- What do we do?
- We keep going.
- We're still on strike.
- What do you mean?
- But you've agreed to everything.
- I was satisfied then - now I'm hungry.
You can shoot us,
but you can't break our resolve.
Let Warsaw know what we said.
No pay rise for those of you
who are still here after 6 pm.
We got what we came here for, but...
I announce a strike of solidarity.
We're staying put!
Don't go away…stay here!
It's not over yet! We're still on strike!
People, stop! Come back! It's not over!
Close the gate!
ZOMO is here. Militarized Militia.
It's Sunday.
There's no one in the shipyard.
People went home,
to their families, to church.
And ZOMO is at the gate.
They can get in.
Bring people back.
How? By force?
We were told the tanks are coming.
They're bringing in the military.
They've set up an extra post for ZOMO
at the local army barracks.
They'll kill us all.
- Let them. There's no going back now!
- I knew we should have taken the money.
I don't give a shit about the 2000 zloty.
You want to be a Soviet slave?
You're asking for trouble, man.
My kids need food on the table...
and they need their father.
- I don't want to get killed.
- And I just want to be free.
You get shit if you ask for too much.
Get yourselves ready!
We're moving in!
ZOMO is all set.
Let's organize a Holy Mass
to bring back the people.
...give us this day our daily bread,
and forgive us our trespasses,
as we forgive those who
trespass against us...
STRIKE DEMANDS
Have you gone mad?
You want them to shoot us all?
- What do you mean?
- A demand for free elections?
They'll go along with no censorship
even if it's a false promise.
They've accepted the pay rises.
- And free trade unions?
- They wouldn't call them 'free'.
Maybe slave trade unions then?
We need to come up with a name
they don't find some fault with.
Make me some coffee.
I've brought some bread.
Lech, militia cars outside the shipyard.
They will get in.
I told you from the start.
- They only want to scare us.
- Or they're getting ready.
- Still no government delegation.
- Who are you afraid of?
- The forces of law and order.
- They're scared, too.
- I wonder who they're scared of.
- Of their minister.
- And the minister?
- Of Gierek.
- And Gierek?
- Of Brezhnev and Moscow.
- And Brezhnev? Of Americans?
- Americans make him laugh.
Isn't he afraid of God?
He's an atheist. Russians
are not even afraid of the devil.
Relax.
They want to see how long we last.
What does it mean to be a leader?
It means being determined.
Inside and out.
I've always been like this.
Even when I was a poor farm boy
who dreamed of being a pilot.
I was always the pack leader.
Like a bull leading a herd.
Watching out for it.
Without a bull, cows scatter
looking for a bit of grass.
Herd without a leader
is a thing with no future.
Although I'm not sure if I'm a leader.
All I know is that I have a gut feeling.
And when the crowd falls silent,
I know what I want to say
and I can choose the right words.
As always, I'd like to say hello
and give you the latest news.
Nothing has changed since
yesterday evening.
So, we're still waiting.
You've got to help us out,
the people on this side are very tired.
Please give us your support,
because if we give up now,
we won't be able to solve
this issue for a long time.
Two professors from Warsaw
are at the gate.
They've brought a letter.
Signed by intellectuals.
- So what?
- Should we let them in?
- Who are they?
- Geremek and Mazowiecki.
They're all right.
They wrote letters of support...
...for the persecuted workers
and risked being abused themselves.
What do we need them for?
For advice. On different things.
Experts?
OK, go get them. Might be useful.
Look, there's nothing about us here.
Work stoppages.
It's the censorship.
We need to get the
foreign press involved.
Where would we get them from?
Here, Sopot.
- Where in Sopot?
- The international music festival.
- Go get them then.
- Me? Let him do it.
He doesn't speak English.
Go!
I welcome the Prime Minister
and the government delegation
on behalf of the Inter-Enterprise
Strike Committee,
which represents 370 industrial plants
and factories.
Our country is currently facing
a difficult economic situation.
The reason is that the workers
have not been properly represented.
We're fighting for our own trade union.
We have a right to one.
Just like our other rights.
And who are those gentlemen over there?
Are they Polish citizens?
It's unprecedented to hold negotiations
on national issues
attended by representatives
of the foreign press.
We are talking about our country,
about Poland.
If they're not accredited
Polish journalists...
Please leave the room, thank you.
I've presented the
commission's detailed views
on the 21 demands of the workers.
As for us, we're all set
and we won't back down.
We simply want a decent life
for everyone.
And now Andrzej Gwiazda will present
our perspective on trade unions.
A free independent trade union will
protect social and material interests
of employees
and will not act as a political party.
We have received the following message:
Miners from coal mines in Silesia
have started a strike of solidarity
with the workers from Gdansk.
Miners from Silesia send their greetings
to the shipyard workers.
The following coal
mines are on strike...
Manifest Lipcowy, Borynia, Jastrzębie...
Now we've got them!
Lech is coming!
- What are you counting on now?
- An earthquake.
You think it's likely?
I always think what I say.
You are at the driving wheel here.
Aren't you afraid of losing control?
I won't lose control.
Let's all behave like decent people,
and everything will be alright.
The right to strike will be guaranteed
in a new regulation about trade unions.
I propose we prepare a press release
stating that we have reached consensus,
that the strike is over
and that work will continue.
Prime Minister, we're almost done,
we'll go through what's left in a flash.
So I suggest... since we have been
waiting for so long...
It's Saturday. Let's keep on
working through Sunday...
to have the agreement ready by Monday.
This is too important to act in a hurry.
We want to go back to work on Monday.
But we have to get it guaranteed
in black and white.
- You will have it in writing.
- "Will have it" isn't the same as having it.
- But we have signed some things...
- Yes, Prime Minister.
That's why I think we're halfway there.
But since we have those signatures...
Of course, but there are still many
unresolved issues.
I have one more proposal to discuss.
As we're really making progress here,
I ask that you do something to stop
the arrests of opposition activists.
Mainly in Warsaw, where many
KOR members have been imprisoned.
I propose we sign a draft
of this press release.
I propose that we stop here.
But please bear in mind
the issue of those arrests.
We've established a good
working relationship.
The arrests are the only thing that stops
us from closing the deal by Monday.
GDAŃSK
31 AUGUST, 1980
Lech, Lech, Lech!
We now have independent
trade unions.
We have the right to strike.
And other rights
will be established soon.
Intercollegiate Strike Committee
Demands
Please remember the people
on this side are really tired.
They want to go home - which I know
will probably boost birth statistics...
What about the prisoners?
All of them are getting out.
I have it all on in writing here.
We have been fighting together
and I haven't thanked you properly.
It hasn't been my fight only.
You have fought, too.
So, let me thank you,
go home now, get some rest, let us
take care of the final arrangements.
Good morning, we're a bit early.
- Good morning.
- It's six forty.
Please come in.
Is this the first time a TV crew
interviews you in bed?
In bed? It's the first time for sure.
What do you think about all this?
Your husband is pretty much a guest here.
He is.
How do you cope with that?
How many children do you have?
We have six kids.
- How old is the oldest?
- 10.
- And the youngest?
- Two months old.
- A baby.
- Right.
Do the neighbors help you out?
In this part of the building, there are
no neighbors. Only offices.
I don't have time
for neighbors anyway.
You say you're tired,
but I see a smiling face.
I need to cope somehow.
What if this situation lasts longer?
And your husband keeps being only a guest?
- I don't know...
- Will you protest?
For sure.
I feel more and more tired,
and I can hardly manage.
But your husband is fighting
for great things.
A family is a great thing, too.
Don't you think so?
Is it not possible to combine
these two great things?
Maybe, but I don't know...
We might find a way. I'm sure we will.
- Thank you very much. Sorry.
- Good bye.
What have you done?
Look at all that cream!
How long will Wałęsa last?
If they don't kill me,
if it all works out...
You want a cold calculation?
I can say that from now on
It's a downward slope for me.
Gentle or maybe steep.
I'll explain why.
I wasn't made for peaceful times
and I can't play by everyday rules.
I can't repeat what I did before.
In 1980 and later.
If something goes wrong in Poland,
people will focus their anger on me.
And the people who praise me now
will start throwing stones.
They will forget I was on their side.
Fighting their fight.
If I was greedy, I'd shave off my mustache
and go back to work in the shipyard.
But I won't do it as long as
'Solidarity' still wants me.
I know that from now on
the situation will only become harder.
Things will get more complicated.
Eat some sandwiches.
They're over there.
The government hasn't kept
its promises.
We seem to be playing both
chess and checkers on one board.
But it's time to play one game now,
and discuss the future of the nation.
What about wildcat strikes?
Let me eat, gentlemen.
Help yourselves.
They started a strike in central Poland.
Do we support it?
I'm not authorizing anything.
Not reading or signing anything.
Tell them we're sorry for their trouble.
Tell them to go back to work.
We've made you the boss and you back down?
This is bullshit, not a free trade union.
- Are you not authorizing the strike?
- This is what the situation demands.
What we need to do is hit them hard.
And not back down.
No more talking to the communists.
Who should I talk to then?
You? We've talked enough.
The Americans don't want to talk.
What would you have me do?
- I'm the one risking everything.
- What about my leg?
Let them give it back to me!
Half a million troops,
100,000 militia men.
You've convinced me. Take your crutches.
Let's go arrest Brezhnev.
- May I have more scrambled eggs?
- You like them?
- Sure! Your wife makes great eggs.
- Danuta, could you fix some more?
What else?
This is not a way to live.
The door is open day and night.
People go in and out.
Good bye, thank you for coming.
Look at the time, gentlemen.
Go on. Good bye.
People coming in like
they own the place!
The neighbor picks Wałęsa over the cops
when her drunk husband misbehaves.
Lech! You have your own family.
You have kids. Remember?
Bogdan was sent to the principal's office.
He tried to start a strike at school.
The other morning, everyone's in pajamas
and there's a camera crew filming!
Have you no shame?
Good bye. Get out of here!
You too!
If you want, I can stick it
on the door.
TYPHUS
NO ENTRY
STRIKE
WHAT ARE WE WAITING FOR?
This is Channel One
of the Polish Radio
Lech Wałęsa, with the approval
of "Solidarity" and the government,
has decided to call off
the general strike...
Turn it off.
This is what the union has come to.
He's basically become a king.
He didn't say he'd break the strike.
But that he might do it.
That he would be held accountable
and would resign if necessary...
We can assume he's going to
break the strike,
Some of the demands will be met.
He'll be the one to save the day.
We now need to decide if the union
should be run by the will of one man
or led by a collective body.
At this point I want to say
we have come up with a good compromise.
Maybe nothing would have happened
but the risk was too high to take.
I don't regret what I have done
even if everyone else disagreed.
Because I know that courage
is nothing without sound judgment.
And I know we've achieved a lot.
I know one thing: people's reactions
when we left the negotiations.
They fell into each other's arms.
They lifted my car up in joy.
Didn't you see that?!
- I did.
- Exactly.
What does the nation want?
Who do you represent?
Who do you want to expose?
As long as I'm here,
I will use all viable options.
I can expose myself,
but not the people.
Where did you learn to think this way?
I don't know.
I've never really read books.
I try but I get bored
by the time I reach page 5.
I've always solved my own problems.
Even repaired my own washing machines.
Lech, what about the intellectuals?
God save us from intellectuals
and peasants!
Now you will probably ask
why I keep all those professors,
advisers and experts around me.
I know if I tried to keep them away
they'd still find a way back in.
So I've chosen to engage them.
It's also convenient to have
intelligent people around.
There's one thing to keep in mind.
You shouldn't feel inferior to them.
And I don't. You know why?
They talk and talk for hours and
their conclusions are the same
as the ones I reach in five seconds.
I'm not too cocky, am I?
Not at all. Why?
I can make that impression.
Is it true you removed your chador
in front of Khomeini?
It's true, I did.
Aren't you afraid of Russian tanks?
And if not Russian, then Polish ones?
No, no, no.
I don't want to think about this.
Why are you saying such horrid things?
There will be no Soviet tanks.
No Soviet tanks.
13 DECEMBER, 1981
The Secretary and the Governor.
I was expecting this.
This is the last nail in your coffin.
We were ordered to take...
to invite you for a friendly chat.
Good evening, Danuta,
we apologize...
They've introduced martial law.
We're taking your husband to Warsaw.
I'm not going anywhere.
If you release other prisoners, I'll go.
Good night, gentlemen.
- So it's happened.
- What now?
They'll be back.
I've packed some stuff just in case.
Open the door! Now!
Or we'll break it down!
Break it down then!
I won't open it.
Bring the other two back
and I'll open the door.
Danuta, don't get scared,
but it could take up to a year.
I'm not scared at all.
Lech,
what if I did get scared?
If you got scared, it would be the end
for me, for the kids, for everyone.
I'm not scared, then.
Not at all.
- I'm scared, too.
- I know.
Open the door, Lech.
Danuta, open up. Wake up the kids.
Let them see the communists
take their father away.
- May we come in?
- You've got a great sense of humour.
Don't any of you catch cold.
Mom can't handle your being sick.
Bogdan, don't get sick again.
Remember!
Where are you going, dad?
I'll be back.
Danuta, please...
One thing, Danuta...
People will turn away from you.
- What are you talking about?
- They will. They're just people.
After you.
One day you'll come begging for a job.
Citizens of the People's
Republic of Poland!
Today I address you
as a soldier and as the head
of the Polish government.
Our homeland is
on the verge of collapse.
Our administrative structures
are no longer effective.
The collapsing economy
is being dealt blow after blow.
Our soldiers' hands are clean.
Our goal is the best
interest of the nation.
The army won't replace
regular socialist democracy.
Anarchy is the enemy of democracy.
We want Poland to be a great country.
Great in terms of culture,
heritage, its position in Europe.
The only way to reach this goal is though
socialism, accepted by the whole Nation.
Poland has not yet perished,
so long as we still live.
What if I shouted I was Lech Wałęsa,
and you've taken me hostage?
Go ahead.
Inspection.
People! I'm Lech Wałęsa.
I've been kidnapped by the communists!
You son of a bitch!
It's all your fault!
Get out of the car!
Fuck off, you bastard!
Still want to get out?
You see, Lech.
Poles are not an easy nation to rule.
ARŁAMÓW
11 MAY, 1982
- Where are we?
- The East.
Confirm the delivery.
- Russian or ours?
- Russian, goddamn it.
Shit. If they take him out,
they take us out. No witnesses. Let's go.
Mr. Wałęsa.
You're finished.
All your buddies are either
in jail or on our side.
Or they're shitting themselves.
The politburo doesn't want to talk to you.
You are a nobody, they say.
Just a regular scoundrel.
They're considering what I call
the model from Czechoslovakia:
tanks stay in the country,
you stay in prison. For 18 years.
But I'd like to give you
one last chance.
- You will go on TV and stop the strikes.
- Oh, so there are strikes?
- You'll apologize for 'Solidarity'.
- I demand to see my advisers.
Did you know that our friends
in the East are wondering
if there's any reason to keep you alive?
Kill me, and people
will make me a saint.
It's gloomy in here.
Please join me, gentlemen.
The more the merrier. Come on.
Do you have a wife and kids?
No, I'm single.
If you're poisoned, it will be
a smaller loss for Poland. Enjoy.
Martial law has stopped those
rushing headlong into a civil war.
The 13th of December
was a shock for everyone.
But it certainly prevented
something far worse.
Most people greeted that day
with understanding and relief.
There is hope again for rebuilding
our deregulated economy.
Some people never learned
their lessons from history.
This is Radio Free Europe,
the voice of free Poland.
Listen!
Solidarity has organized rallies
in all major Polish cities.
The authorities ordered a brutal
suppression of all demonstrations by ZOMO.
Tear gas, water cannons, and
armored vehicles were used.
...many have been wounded...
Mr. Wałęsa!
- Why exactly am I interned?
- What are you talking about?
You are not an internee.
- What am I then?
- You are the government's guest.
- Officially.
- So I can leave. Good bye then.
You will go on TV.
You'll condemn the strikes,
apologize for 'Solidarity'
and agree to join the executive
board of a NEW trade union.
- What if I don't?
- What?
What if I don't?
That's not an option.
You have the key to your own freedom.
Yes or no?
- You're not a good politician.
- I'm just an electrician.
Good bye.
- Is it going to be a portable altar?
- A field altar, my son.
Will you take part in the Mass, boys?
We don't have time.
We need to keep an eye on you.
- Praised be Jesus Christ.
- Forever and ever.
I'm afraid this is my last visit.
They want to punish you this way.
They see your advisers
and react like the devil to holy water.
They want to cut you off
from everybody. I beg you, son,
think about writing to our leader,
General Jaruzelski,
ask him to let you out.
The Polish nation needs you.
I didn't ask him to lock me up,
I will not ask him to set me free.
There's no shame in it.
Even the Pope has sent
a letter to the general.
No, no, no!
But the general didn't answer.
A letter from Danuta.
I have the Pope's Encyclical for you.
- You should read it.
- No need.
I agree with everything the Pope says.
I'm afraid I have to show you this,
as much as it pains me.
Who is Lech Wałęsa?
He is a Security Service agent.
A pharisee and a scoundrel.
During the December 1970 riots,
he informed on his colleagues,
including Anna Walentynowicz.
His master stroke was laying
the foundations for martial law.
Easy, son. This announcement,
supposedly written by 'Solidarity',
is really distributed
by the Security Service.
They even delivered this
to the Norwegian embassy.
Brezhnev, the Leader
of the Soviet Union is Dead
Lech Wałęsa Released From Internment
Dad's coming back.
They've released him!
The streets are empty.
It's 3 in the morning.
People need to sleep before work.
I was supposed to pick you up
earlier, but there was no car.
Don't make me laugh.
I'm glad you didn't tell me to walk.
He's coming! He's coming!
He's mine now.
We'll stick a TYPHOID sign
on the door.
Come say hello to your dad!
You're all grown up! Come on!
TYPHOID
NO ENTRY
Solidarity! Solidarity!
Thank you for coming!
Thank you for always believing
in 'Solidarity'!
Solidarity! Solidarity!
First objection:
why was I taken from my home?
- If you don't want to come to us...
- Then why am I here?
- How are you?
- How do you think I am?
- You're looking good.
- You too.
There's news about you
coming from abroad.
What news exactly?
They talk about your meeting with
leaders of the clandestine 'Solidarity'.
Give me the case number
and we'll talk.
- Did you meet them?
- I have the right to meet anyone I want.
But did you exercise this right?
- Maybe I did, maybe I didn't.
- Did this meeting take place or not?
There are 30 people watching me.
You should know my every move.
Did this meeting take place?
We want to know your opinion of it.
Why was I taken from my home?
- I want specifics.
- Give me the case number.
I'm not telling you if the meeting
took place.
It would have been a good idea
for me to be there.
Then I will interrogate
you as a witness.
- You will answer my questions.
- I will or I won't. I'll decide.
- You're obligated to answer.
- I'll see if I'm obligated or not.
Did you inform foreign agencies
about the meeting
with the coordinators
of underground 'Solidarity'?
I will not answer this question.
Do you know of anyone else who
might have contacted foreign agencies?
I refuse to answer this question.
As a free man, I can meet anyone
and do anything I please.
I would argue that there's a limit
to doing as you please.
- You have nothing on me.
- Put it on the record:
- "That's all I have to say."
- Right!
End of report, date, time,
and so on...
Should I read it aloud
before you sign?
No, I will not sign it.
You didn't tell me
in what case I'm a witness.
This case is not about the meeting.
- It is.
- No, it's not.
That's how you see it.
I'm not going to argue with you.
"After reading, I confirm
the report is consistent
with my testimony."
I also confirm I understand nothing.
I can add that you refuse to sign
the statement. What reason do I put down?
I don't sign anything.
That's my rule.
I won't believe it until
I hear it myself.
Nobel Committee has awarded
Nobel Peace Prize to Lech Wałęsa...
Congratulations!
The Nobel Committee has decided
to award Lech Wałęsa...
Yes, we're very pleased.
...yet again supporting
a confrontational game
this time against Poland
and against socialism.
Tiny article. Small print.
Right. Let me hand him the phone.
Someone from the Norwegian embassy.
No, my decision is final.
I can't, because they won't let me
back into the country when I return.
Danuta will go.
That's my wife.
That's the best solution.
Thank you. Have a nice day, too.
It'll be OK.
OSLO
10 DECEMBER, 1983
Your Majesty, Your Excellencies,
distinguished representatives
of the Norwegian Nation.
You know why I can't be here
to receive the honorable prize.
- Something to declare?
- The Nobel Prize and a medal.
- And my son's new skis.
- Money? Fur? Silver? Gold?
Are you looking for money?
I left everything in Oslo.
The chatty lady will go through
a personal inspection.
Halina?
Please follow my colleague.
Are you free? Let's go.
This is a personal inspection
according to the Polish customs law.
Do you have anything on you
that you haven't declared?
- No. Nothing.
- Empty your pockets.
Dad, when will Mom come?
In a minute.
- Is that it?
- Take off your underwear.
Panties.
Crouch please.
She's coming!
Mom's coming!
What took you so long?
Personal inspection.
Lech, take the suitcase.
I thought we'd go
to Jasna Góra Sanctuary.
We'll thank the Black Madonna,
leave the medal as a votive offering.
Why do you want me to tell you
all this? I have a headache.
I do, too.
The nation is ready to blow up
like a bomb.
I know how to stop it.
The point is to go against the crowd.
Patiently.
Last question: you said, when
the communist government falls,
'Solidarity' will take over and you
should take control of everything.
Yes, I did say that.
So you were not joking.
Do you think you're capable of that?
Yes, I believe I am.
Do you believe the communist party
in this country would accept that?
Would they have any other choice
if the government fell?
But this is what I say today.
Tomorrow - we'll see.
What would the Soviets say?
Your brothers and allies?
That's exactly the problem.
That's why I think we're discussing
an unrealistic, fantastical possibility.
Thank you, Lech.
Thank you from the bottom of my heart.
It has been a pleasure talking to you.
Despite the headaches you gave me.
Good luck, Lech.
Solidarity! Solidarity!
AFTER YEARS OF STRUGGLE,
"SOLIDARITY", LED BY LECH WAŁĘSA,
MANAGED TO ORGANISE ROUND TABLE
TALKS WITH THE AUTHORITIES
WARSAW
5 APRIL, 1989
Our country is ruined.
It's difficult for
working people to live.
It sure wasn't done by the fairies,
but a system we did not choose.
We came to sit at this
table from prisons.
Look at that!
He got away in the end.
We remember all those
who shed their blood for 'Solidarity'.
Don't worry.
We'll get him eventually.
I think these talks
can be the beginning
of democracy and a free Poland.
And a democratic election
is the first step.
Solidarity's "Gazeta Wyborcza"
8 pages of truth, 8 pages of freedom.
Support Lech Wałęsa's Team!
Vote for 'Solidarity'!
IN JUNE 1989 ELECTIONS
TO BOTH HOUSES OF PARLIAMENT
BROUGHT VICTORY TO "SOLIDARITY".
POLAND PAVED THE WAY TO FREEDOM
FOR OTHER COMMUNIST BLOCK COUNTRIES
ON 9 NOVEMBER, 1989 THE BERLIN WALL FELL.
A NEW EUROPE WAS BORN
WASHINGTON D.C.,
15 NOVEMBER, 1989